Terrence Kaufman Preliminary Inventory
University of Texas Libraries,
Terrence Kaufman Preliminary Inventory
1960-2010
Archive of Indigenous Languages of Latin America
2010-03
62 boxes
Benson Latin American Collection, The University of Texas at Austin
Analog copies of indigenous language recordings, field notes, photographs, and other research material collected and digitized by the University of Texas' Archive of Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA)
Historical Note
Archive of Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA) was founded in 2000 by Joel Sherzer of the Department of Anthropology, Anthony Woodbury of the Department of Linguistics, and Mark McFarland, Director of the Digital Library Services Division of the UT General Library System. The pilot website and database, launched in April, 2000, were built by a group of Sherzer's graduate students: Christine Beier, William Fairchild, Ajb'ee Jimenez, and Lev Michael. The first year of the project was supported by a grant from the Dean of the College of Liberal Arts at UT Austin.
Joel Sherzer conducted research on the Kuna language of Panama for more than 30 years. Over the years he amassed a sizeable collection of recordings of Kuna discourse, including performances that are of tremendous importance to the Kuna people. He observed that other scholars were also creating substantial collections of recordings and texts, constituting a tremendous resource for the indigenous languages of Latin America. He was concerned about the preservation of these priceless collections of indigenous verbal art.
The development of affordable technologies for creating and using digital media make it possible for AILLA to collect, digitize, and permanently preserve these resources in standard formats that anyone can access through widely-available software tools. The Internet makes it possible to serve these resources to a global audience, that most importantly includes the speakers of the languages represented in the archive.
AILLA is part of both the Lozano Long Institute of Latin American Studies (LLILAS) and the Nettie Lee Benson Latin American Collection (BLAC) at the University of Texas at Austin. AILLA is also an integral part of the language documentation programs of the departments of Linguistics and Anthropology.
AILLA is supported by the University of Texas at Austin's College of Liberal Arts and the University Libraries. We are also grateful for generous support from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the National Science Foundation. The archive proper is housed on servers maintained by the Digital Library Services Division of the University Libraries. AILLA's lab and office are located inside the Benson.
Scope and Contents Note
Analog originals of indigenous language recordings, field notes, photographs, and other research materials collected and digitized by AILLA. The collection is roughly organized by the name of each depositor of collection material. Country coverage,languages, and dates are listed when available.
All of the analog materials described below have been digitized. Access to the corresponding digital collections should be done through the links listed below in the Inventory.
Access Restrictions
Boxes 1-13 of this collection are stored remotely. Advance notice is required for retrieval. Please contact bensonspecialcollections@austin.utexas.edu.
Digital access to the materials described below is provided digitally through the Archive of Indigenous Language of Latin American website at http://www.ailla.utexas.org. For questions please contact the AILLA manager at ailla@ailla.utexas.org.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Material
Joel F. Sherzer Collection on Guna Linguistics
Mary Ritchie Key Papers
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Archive of Indigenous Languages of Latin America--Archives
Subjects
Indigenous languages--Sources
Places
Mexico; Guatemala; Argentina; Chile; Bolivia; El Salvador; Colombia; Brazil
Box Inventory
- Terrence Kaufman Preliminary Inventory
  - Tacuapan Nahuatl, 2002-2009; 4 fileslip boxes, 1 folder of loose papers (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s)in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Akateko (knj); Ch'ol (ctu); Chinantec, San Jual Lealao (cle); Chocholtec (coz); Chontal, Highland Oaxaca (chd); Chuj (cac), Huarijío (var), Huave, San Mateo del Mar (huv); Mayo (mfy); Mazateco, Chiquihuitlán (maq); Mixe, Tlahuitoltepec (mxp); Mixteco, Piñoles (mil); Me'phaa, Malinaltepec (tcf); Nahuatl, Acaxochitlán (nhe); Nahuatl, Istmo-Pajapan (nhp); Otomí, San Andrés Cuexcontitlán (ots); Triqui, Copala (trc); Totonac, Papantla (top); Zapotec, Isthmus (zai); Zoque, Santa María Chimalapa (zoh)
    The Project for the Documentation of the Languages of MesoAmerica (PDLMA):
    AILLA site.
  - Lacandon, 1971-1973; undated; 4 fileslip boxes, 3 folders of paper, each containing photocopies of a notebook (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Mexico, El Salvador. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Nahuatl, Morelos (nhm); Pipil (ppl)
  - Lacandon, 1981-1988; 3 folders, 4 cassettes (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Huasteco (hus)
    Digital collection via
  - Fock, Neils, 1950s; 8 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Brazil. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Waiwai (waw)
  - Gerzenstein, Ana, 1966; 1968,; 1971,; 1977,; 1983-1985; 9 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Argentina. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Chorote (crt); Maká (mca); Wichí Lhamtés Vejoz (wlv)
  - Golluscio, Lucía, 1968; 1978,; 1981-1985; 9 reel-to-reel tapes, 1 cassette (Box 1)
    Country Coverage: Argentina. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Wichí Lhamtés Vejoz (wlv); Mapudungun (arn)
  - Grimes, Larry, late 1960s, early 1970s; 6 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 2)
    Country Coverage: Guatemala. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): K'iche' (quc); Kaqchikel (cak); Tz'utujil (tzj)
  - Grinevald, Colette, 1970-1973; 5 reel-to-reel tapes, 11 cassettes, 1 mini disk (Box 2)
    Country Coverage: Guatemala. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Popti' (jac)
  - Hill, Jane and Kenneth, 1962; 1974-1978,; 1983; 90 cassette tapes, plus folders and notebooks (Box 2-4)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Nahuatl, Central (nhn)
  - Hopkins, Nicholas, 1964-2002; 30 reel-to-reel tapes, 9 cassette tapes (Box 4)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Ch'ol (ctu); Chuj (cac); Unspecified language (und)
  - Josserand, Kathryn, 1970s and 1980s; 118 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 4-6)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Mixtec (omq); various Otomí, Eastern Highland (otm); Mazahua, Central (maz)
  - Lastra, Yolanda, 1959-2009; 13 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 7)
    Country Coverage: Mexico, Bolivia. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Nahuatl (nah); Nahuatl, Central (nhn); Nahuatl, Central Huasteca (nch); Nahuatl, Huaxcaleca (nhq); Nahuatl, Morelos (nhm) Nahuatl, Central Puebla (ncx); Nahuatl, Northern Puebla (ncj); Nahuatl, Southeastern Puebla (nhs); Otomí (otm); Otomí, Ixtenco (otz); Quechua, South Bolivian (qwe)
  - Martín, Herminia, 6 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 7)
    Country Coverage: Argentina. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Chorote (crt); Nivaclé (cag); Pilagá (plg); Wichí Lhamtés Vejoz (wlv)
  - Messineo, Christina, 2003; 3 cassette tapes (Box 7)
    Country Coverage: Argentina. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Qom (qom)
  - Moser, Edward and Mary, 1960s; 38 open reel tapes (Box 7)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Seri (sei)
  - Pride, Kitty and Leslie, 1960s; 8 reel-to-reel tapes, 1 cassette (Box 8)
    Country Coverage: Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Chatino, Eastern San Juan Quiahije (ctp); Chatino, Tataltepec de Valdés (cta)
  - Suárez, Jorge A., 1960s; 1970s; 30 reel-to-reel tapes, notebooks (Box 8)
    Country Coverage: Argentina, Chile. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Ona (ona); Tehuelche (teh)
  - Hopkins, Nicholas, 1964-2002; 21 DAT, 9 open reel tapes, 13 Hi-8 video cassettes, 44 audio cassettes (Box 9)
  - Lastra, Yolanda, 1959-2009; 25 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 10)
  - Martin, Laura, 1973-2005; 117 cassettes, 9 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 11)
    Country Coverage: Guatemala, Mexico. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Mocho (mhc); Q'anjob'al (kjb); Tektiteko (ttc)
  - Martin, Laura, 1973-2005; 101 folders containing dissertation and other research data, in addition to transcriptions and translations that correspond to audio files; each folder has an PID written on it; also includes an unfoldered copy of Terrence Kaufman’s November 1967 “Preliminary Mochó Vocabulary” (Box 12)
  - Martin, Laura, 1973-2005; 2.75 inches of publications by other people; 11 notebooks of fieldnotes and elicitations (Box 13)
  - Hill, Jane and Kenneth, 1962; 1974-1978,; 1983; 9 folders of various publications and a few unfoldered pamphlets and publications (Box 13)
  - Dakin, Karen, 1971-1973; 6 reel-to-reel tapes (Box 13)
  - Sorensen, Arthur, To be eventually included in a stand alone collection. (Box 14-16)
    Country Coverage: Colombia. Language Name(s) in English (ISO 639-3 code(s)): Curripaco (kpc); Wanano (gvc); Tucano (tuo); Desano (des); Cubeo (cub); Multiple languages (mul)